<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
     xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
     xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
     xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
     xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
     >
  <channel>
    <title>mojavy.com</title>
    <link>http://mojavy.com/blog</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2013 20:15:36 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>Blogofile</generator>
    <sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
    <sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
    <item>
      <title>sailing stones</title>
      <link>http://mojavy.com/blog/2013/06/16/sailing-rock/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2013 20:15:36 JST</pubDate>
      <category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mojavy.com/blog/2013/06/16/sailing-rock/</guid>
      <description>sailing stones</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img alt="sailing-stone" src="/images/sailing-stone.png" /> </p>
<p>アメリカのデスバレーには <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sailing_stone">Sailing stone</a> という不思議現象があるらしい。</p>
<p>何十キロもあるような石が勝手に移動するというもので、</p>
<p>どういう原理で動くのか長年よくわかっていなかった</p>
<p>水が少しだけたまったときに、
石のまわりに氷ができて、
石が少し浮く
完全にはうかないけど風でうごく程度
計算してみるとまあまあ妥当な結果になった</p>
<p>Further understanding of the geologic processes at work in Racetrack
Playa goes hand in hand with technological development. In 2009,
development of inexpensive time-lapse digital cameras allowed the
capturing of transient meteorological phenomena including dust devils
and playa flooding.[8] These cameras, cheap for their high amount of
memory capacity, were aimed at capturing various stages of the
previously mentioned phenomena, though discussion of the sliding
stones ensued. The developers of photographic technology describe the
difficulty of capturing the Racetrack’s stealthy rocks, as movements
only occur one in three years and last approximately ten
seconds. Their next identified advancement is wind-triggered imagery,
vastly reducing the ten million seconds of non-transit time they must
sift through.  In a study published in 2011 it is postulated that
small rafts of ice form around the rocks and when the local water
level rises, the rocks are buoyantly floated off the soft bed thus
reducing the reaction and friction forces at the bed. Since this
effect depends on reducing friction, and not on increasing the wind
drag, these ice cakes need not have a particularly large surface area
if the ice is adequately thick, as the minimal friction allows the
rocks to be moved by arbitrarily light winds.[6][9] Theft of
rocks[edit] On 30 May 2013, the LA Times reported that park officials
are looking in to the theft of several of the rocks.[10]</p>
<p>http://www.core77.com/blog/transportation/scientist_figures_out_how_those_big-ass_sailing_stones_move_themselves_across_death_valley_25038.asp</p>
<p>We suggest that the existence of many of the rock-carved trails at
Racetrack Playa in Death Valley National Park is predominantly due to
the effect of arbitrarily weak winds on rocks that are floated off the
soft bed by small rafts of ice, as also occurs in arctic tidal beaches
to form boulder barricades. These ice cakes need not have a
particularly large surface area if the ice is adequately thick—the ice
cakes allow the rocks to move by buoyantly reducing the reaction and
friction forces at the bed, not by increasing the wind drag. The
parameter space of ice thickness and extent versus rock size for
flotation is calculated and found to be reasonable. We demonstrate the
effect with a simple experiment.</p>
<hr />
<p>"Racetrack Playa" sounds like the screenname of an online teenager
you're competing against in Need for Speed, but scientists recognize
it as the name of a dried-up lake in Death Valley. For a century,
scientific minds have been puzzled by a well-documented,
poorly-understood phenomenon occuring at Racetrack Playa: Enormous
stones, some up to 700 pounds, appear to have somehow moved themselves
across the lakebed floor in random patterns, leaving a furrowed trail
behind them.</p>
<p>No one had ever seen these "sailing stones" move, but many
photographed the end result. The original thought was that the lakebed
forms a thin sheet of ice on it, and that the wind then blows the
rocks across it; but that theory was discounted after researchers
calculated it would take wind speeds of hundreds of miles per hour to
move the rocks, while the wind at the Racetrack maxes out around 90
m.p.h. And if you're wondering why they don't just strap a GoPro
camera onto a rock to see what's going on, scientists returning to the
site over the years have calculated that the rocks move for short
periods of time, just once every three years. That's a bit longer than
your battery's likely to last.</p>
<p>However, a fortunate collision between two of these magic rocks
provided planetary scientist Ralph Lorenz with an interesting
discovery:</p>
<p>Lorenz, studying the trails left by the stones, observed that one rock
had collided against another and been deflected. "There was a rock
trail and it looked like it hit another rock and bounced, but the
trail didn't go all the way up to other the rock, like it was repelled
somehow," Lorenz told Smithsonian Magazine. In other words, there was
some kind of force-field-like barrier around each rock that prevented
total contact.</p>
<p>What would spontaneously form a barrier around a rock, then later
disappear? Lorenz realized that as moisture levels changed with the
seasons, a collar of ice could form around the rock. With the rest of
the lakebed covered in a thin, cold-but-not-frozen sheet of water,
this ice collar would enable the rock it encased to float—slightly. It
would lift it to the top of the water, but the rock's bottom, the part
that was resting directly on the ground, would not have ice on
it. Wind could then blow the rock across the water, and the bottom of
the rock would dig a furrow into the lakebed. Later the ice and water
would melt and recede.</p>
<p>Eventually, Lorenz employed a tried-and-true method for testing his
nascent idea: the kitchen-table experiment. "I took a small rock, and
put it in a piece of Tupperware, and filled it with water so there was
an inch of water with a bit of the rock sticking out," he says. "I put
it in the freezer, and that then gave me a slab of ice with a rock
sticking out of it." He flipped the rock-ice hybrid upside down and
floated it in a tray of water with sand on the bottom. By merely
blowing gently on the ice, he realized, he could send the embedded
rock gliding across the tray, scraping a trail in the sand as it
moved. After decades of theoretical calculations by countless
scientists, the answer seemed to be sitting on his tabletop.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
